this is software engineering radio a
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
[Music]
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program welcome listeners
to another episode of software
engineering radio this one is another
language episode it's not necessarily
about a new language but it's about a
bunch of new features for a new version
of that language it's about c++ o x or
whatever the correct pronunciation is
our guest today is scott Meyers and well
hi Scott
good morning hello well why don't you
introduce yourself well to our listeners
so they they know who you are maybe they
already know because you've written a
couple of books but who knows alrighty i
am scott Meyers and I've been working
with C++ for a distressingly a long time
I think it's over 20 years at this point
and I've written some books on on using
C++ and I do consulting and training on
C++ and compared to many other people
I'm not a multiple language guy I'm
really pretty much focused on C++ I have
some other interests in terms of
software quality and high performance
programming but it usually ends up
coming back to C++ mmm-hmm I always
found it interesting that C++ is one of
the languages that we're where people
can make a living being a consultant
about the language for example for Java
that's that's not the case you have to
be some Java Enterprise framework person
or whatever but you can't make a living
from the language itself I wonder if
this is a good or a bad sign for the
language well you limit this way I think
it is indicative of the complexity of
the language yes my my view of all
programming languages including C++ is
it effectively they are tools to help
programmers get a job done and
essentially C++ is it a very large very
complicated very powerful tool and my
job in many cases is to help people
understand how they can make the best
use of that tool in solving whatever
problems they want to solve yeah okay so
C++ o X is the is the new standard
is it already finalized no it's not
finished
in fact about a week ago they came out
with what's called the final committee
draft which essentially says we now know
everything is going to be in the
language we've mailed down most of the
details of what the new revised standard
is going to look like but there's still
a few things to work out at this point
the expectation or at least the hope I
guess is that it'll be finished
officially in 2011 okay but practically
speaking for programmers who want to
know what the new versions gonna look
like they now know what it's gonna look
like and more importantly for compiler
and library vendors who want to know
basically what the language is gonna
look like they also have something they
can start implementing yeah and the Oh X
is it you know a hint at hexadecimal or
is it does it mean 2000 and something
with the idea of being only one digit at
the end of the something I mean is it
intended to be the mm something standard
well yeah it's it's a sign of youthful
idealism the original was that it would
be finished by 2009 and obviously they
did not achieve 2009 so officially it's
gonna at this point be done in either
2011 or possibly 2012 but there's been a
lot of jokes about how X is going to be
a hex digit I was really sort of hoping
that they would finish in 2010 because
then we could have said that X was the
Roman numeral oh yeah we didn't we
didn't we didn't achieve that
unfortunately okay and so why why has it
been started I mean although there is no
hype anymore around C++ at least not in
the circles that I deal with
I guess C++ is still a relevant language
and and there was a reason to do a
revision on it right I mean there was
need to improve it well the original
standard for C++ was effectively
finished in 1997 and it was officially
standardised in 1998 you know so we're
well over a decade past that and you
know in the past decade if you think
about all the kinds of changes that have
occurred in computing most notably
things like multi-core development and
stuff like that but also just the rise
of the web and lots of other things the
way in which you use programming
languages and
has really changed in the past decade
and it became very clear you know even
in five years after the standard that
they were going to have to start making
some changes to it and so originally the
standardization committee put a lot of
attention on addressing how to augment
the standard libraries would be more
library facilities and so in 2005 they
came out with something called tr1
which stands for technical report one
and it is essentially a list of 14
fairly substantial new kinds of
functionality added the standard library
and however even at that point C++ did
not officially have something that's
supported for example concurrency so if
nothing else it was very obvious that
the language was gonna have to be
updated to at least officially
acknowledge the existence of parallelism
yeah yeah I guess that has always been
maybe it's too much to call it a problem
but I mean we know from the Java and the
dotnet worlds that the libraries have
you know are standardized and and
they're they contain a lot of stuff so
basically everything you really need
every day is standardized and that
hasn't been that the case for C++ and
comparin sees one aspect of that
concurrency is one aspect C++ is sort of
interesting in that it's really gone off
in its own way in a couple of areas and
if you look at for example Java or C
sharp as sort of the two obvious
examples they have these very very
extensive collections of standard
libraries and so I think that for people
who are writing programs in those
languages and I'm not experts in this
language by any means but a lot of the
work consists of identifying which
standard components we'll mostly get you
where you want to go and then figuring
out how to make them talk to one another
yes and C++ has a comparatively
impoverished standard library as a
result people write a lot more code from
scratch on the other hand C++ has put a
lot of work into things like generic
programming the template based stuff
which has as I said taken off kind of in
a different direction and a lot of that
shows in C++ I works yeah okay so let's
take a somewhat closer look at oh x2 any
like general direction that you can
identify maybe well obviously in
addition to concurrency they're kind of
coherent story - to the C++ effects or
is it a set of kind of inter independent
you know additions um you know I'll tell
you the truth it's interesting and I
should mention right now I am NOT on the
standardization committee and I have
never been on the standardization
committee so I sort of sit and look at
C++ to some degree as an outsider and
about a year ago when I first sat down
and said well it looks like C++ Oh X is
now getting to the point where people
can start to use it so let me sit down
and sort of familiarize myself with this
newer version of the language and I
thought you know it's gonna be kind of
an update this is an enormous change of
the language the the new standard is
going to be twice as big almost as the
old standard so in addition to adding
fairly important things like support for
concurrency and a lot of different kinds
of support for generalization
there's also goodies that make programs
just a lot easier to write in general
there's ways of unifying the syntax so
when I sat down to try to figure out how
to make sense of C++ so X I broke it
into three parts and one of the parts
was what I call features for everybody
which is just useful if you're writing
any kind of C++ program and then a
collection of features that I call
features for class authors which are
additional features which make it easier
to write classes and then there's a
third set of features which I call
features for library authors so there's
um there's not one consistent story
because there's a lot of different
things going on simultaneously it's a
very substantial upgrade to the language
okay so I guess that will make sure that
you'll have enough work to do with a big
and complex language for the next 10-15
years
III think that there is a adequate
ground there yes okay so well obviously
we can't cover every little detail and
every addition and obviously only to you
know a certain depth but we have
identified actually you have identified
a bunch of important you know the main
editions of the new standard and we're
basically going to walk through them and
you'll try to explain to me what it
means and then we'll hope that the rest
of the audience you know if I understand
it they understand it that's the idea
okay fair enough
okay so I guess let's let's get started
with concurrency it's obviously
the big story that everybody really
needs to need to know how to do it in
C++ what's what's going on there you
know what's interesting about the
concurrency stuff is that you can sort
of start at a very high level or you can
start at a very low level and so just
just for kicks I guess I'm going to
start at the high level and work my way
down from there so the first thing is
from a programmers perspective you get
to assume that the language actually
knows what concurrency is which doesn't
sound terribly interesting but it
provides you with a lot of guarantees
you might not otherwise have so for
example C++ has static objects which can
be global objects or they can be inside
classes or whatever and they have to be
initialized exactly once and so one of
the things that C++ now will guarantee
you is that those things are going to be
initialized in a thread safe manner okay
which you should be able to take for
granted but in the past you have not
been able to take that for granted so so
that basically things just naturally
work that you should be able to expect
would work but in the past again there
was no guarantee if you want to for
example just spawn off a a new task say
I want to run this thing asynchronously
and just have it run there was a really
easy way to do that there's a library
call now called async and you simply say
this is what I want to run
asynchronously and these are the
arguments that you pass to it but what I
did want to mention about async because
it represents in some ways some of these
ideas I mentioned before about
generalization is that when you call a
sink conceptually what you say is here's
a function I want you to run and here
are some arguments that I would like you
to pass to the argument to that function
when it runs however you don't have to
pass a function it turns out you can
pass anything that is callable so is
what we call function objects in C++ so
it could be a function it can be a
function pointer it can be a function
object it could be a bound member
function basically anything that is
executable is something which now can be
run remotely and they're all treated the
same way okay you said remotely remote
asynchronously
I'm sorry asynchronously it gives me I
thought there was even more magic to it
my mistake is asynchronously and then
the second thing which is kind of
interesting about that as I said you
didn't pass a set of arguments and it
turns out that you can pass whatever
arguments you want of whatever types you
want and you can pass as many of them as
you want and those will all
be passed automatically in a type safe
manner so how's that how would I have to
imagine the syntax for that I mean if I
can pass in all kinds of things that
needs to be some kind of unified syntax
for doing that do I just write like a
method call and put the async keyword
around it or hardware do it you
essentially you say async which is a
non-member function call and then you
you give the name of whatever you want
to execute so your function pointer or a
function object whatever it happens to
be yeah and then you just have a comma
separated lot of parameters okay I see
hmm and so so it's it's very very simple
from a user's perspective and
automatically the whole issue of firing
up a new thread and getting it running
on a new thread and doing all the types
of passing of arguments all that kind of
stuff managing the lifetime of those
arguments to make sure that they exist
long enough more than I am function to
execute it all that stuff is handled
automatically okay so that's async now
so that's at the highest level and just
for kicks I'll jump now down to the very
lowest level at the very lowest level
there are a whole collection of atomic
data types that allow you to do
manipulations on data types with the
assumption there's going to be an atomic
operation the lowest level of those
things are going to presumably map to
machine hardware so if you have let's
say an atomic int or an atomic Bulli and
something like that you should
reasonably be able to assume that that's
going to map to a machine instruction
assuming there is a machine instruction
which does the right thing this however
has also been generalized so that
there's a template for Atomics and it
turns out that if you happen to need a
specific kind of atomic that the machine
doesn't support so maybe it's a 64-bit
integer or something like that you can
use the same syntax for that and the
underlying library will automatically
implement that for you probably by
creating a mutex to lock/unlock that so
you get atomic operations can I also do
this for complex structure complex alike
structs or something or hope you can do
it anything that you want to okay you
can it basically is is because it's a
template it'll take any dated support
certain operations sounds a little bit
like transactional memory I don't think
it's like transactional memory in the
sense that there's no set well there's
no such thing as an abort for example
it's
it's more a matter of this is a set of
operations I want to execute with mutual
exclusion yeah but for example if an
exception were to be thrown in the
middle of that then you would release
the mutual j'en but that you're not
going to undo anything that had already
been done at that point I see okay so
it's not fractional memory and I and can
I put and can also modify several
independent data structures is there
some kind of bracket I can put around
something or do we have to do that with
mutexes then with low-level programming
you typically would do that with mutex
is the idea behind Atomics is that for
example if you wanted to write a lock
free algorithm then the idea and atomic
in theory will give you that assuming
that the Machine gives you the Atomics
that you want yeah but because so much
programming in C++ is done with
templates which means you don't know the
exact type that you are dealing with
it's very important to be able to just
sort of say I'm going to assume the T is
atomic although I don't exactly know
what T is and I'm going to manipulate
using the atomic interface okay mm-hmm
and then the other thing I wanted to
mention which is different I think from
other programming languages at least the
ones that I've heard of is the
underlying hardware will often have what
are known as relaxed memory models and
relaxed memory models means that the
hardware gets to reorder the loads and
stores the inter what's happening the
underlying machine so for example in
your program you might say I'm gonna set
X to - I'm gonna say X gets Y and then
I'm gonna say you know a gets B and
that's what you write program and it's
possible that the Machine actually
executes X gets Y first and a gets B
second however the underlying hardware
unless it is constrained on some
machines may decide that it's actually
going to do the load - a first excuse me
the store - a first and the store - X
second in other words it may reorder
these loads or reorder these stores and
this can turn out to be an important
capability for certain kinds of fairly
specialized programming and in in C++ by
default you get what's known as program
order which means things behave the way
that a sane human being expects them to
behave yep however if
turns out that you know certain kinds of
for example if you know that X and ay
are completely independent which means
it doesn't matter what order they
actually get written in then you'd like
to give the underlying hardware
permission to do those kinds of
reorderings because in some cases that
can yield a performance improvement and
the underlying Atomics actually allows
certain kinds of I'm going to call them
attributes but that's not quite the
right word that allow you to specify to
the underlying compiler code exactly
what kind of reorderings are permitted
or are not permitted mm-hmm and I think
this is very much in line with the
traditional notion of using c and c++
for very specific high performance work
is you still have a lot of control over
what goes on yeah yeah so that's the
high level stuff for concurrency and the
low level stuff for concurrency and in
between there's just there's there's a
whole bunch of stuff there's mutexes
that we mentioned in passing
there's condition variables that we
mentioned in passing it's got support
for timeouts it's got support for what
are known as promises and futures which
essentially is a communications channel
between an asynchronous thread of
execution so you can talk back and forth
between a caller and a collie there's a
way of bundling those together in
certain conveners called a package to
task I I think most well I know what a
future is and I guess most people know
it it's basically a return value which
you can later query for the actual
return value once it's a synchronously
provided what is a promise a promise is
the other let me put it this way a
future is what a caller gets yes so so
you you spawn an asynchronous threat of
execution and then you wait for the
answer and what you get back is a future
yeah
a promise is what is used by the collie
to deposit the return value into the
future so the promise in some sense is
how you get a value into a future that's
the other end of the wormhole the other
end of the pipe yeah and it turns out
that you may for example you might
decide that what you want to do is have
three different threads all which are
trying to compute some answer for you in
a different way and whichever one does
it first gets to to give the the
solution to the future okay
that's that's one of the things that it
lets you do okay cool sounds good
okay so anything else in the in the
concurrency space III I see that there
is an you know everybody else talks
about functional programming and
immutable data structures and message
passing because shared memory is evil at
least some people say that there is no
such revolutionary change to the C++
language in that and that no there is no
such revolutionary change the people in
the committee certainly took a look at
that and you know I think what they
decided was that in keeping with the
philosophy of being able to do very very
low-level stuff they wanted to give you
the building blocks to build whatever
you wanted to for example unfortunately
in C++ of X there isn't even something
like a thread pool okay however there
are the underlying building blocks so
you can build all that kind of stuff
so essentially C++ effects puts the
foundation in place for building higher
level abstractions and if you later
decide you want to have a message
passing architecture or whatever rate
you build it on top of this yeah and and
since you mentioned thread pools can I
plug in a thread pool into the async
facility so that the async doesn't start
new threats all the time but rather uses
a thread pool that I provided with
certain policies and characteristics
there's no way to specifically plug that
in now what you could do is you could
write your own implementation of async I
do that but but effectively async is
part of the standard library so you are
going to be you know at the mercy of
your standard library implementer but
they could provide a kind of interface
with which I can configure the
implementation of the standard library
which would then be vendor specific or
something exactly they could give you
that kind of an expansion hope they
wanted to okay so I guess let's move on
to the next topic there by the way in no
particular order and the next one I
wrote down is Auto type or Auto typing
implicitly type variables are also known
as type inference right I guess you call
the process is type inference Auto is in
my opinion going to be the thing that
will that most programmers will notice
most quickly and will fall in love with
the fastest okay because what it is that
you no longer have to specify the type
of a variable as long
that variable is given an initialization
value so basically instead of saying
something like you know vector event : :
const iterator i equals some expression
which is something you have had you
write in the past you'll just be able to
say auto i equals that expression and it
automatically will have the correct type
yeah
and that's of course not well if you
think about int and shorts then this is
not a very interesting feature because
the word int is shorter than the word
Auto but if you have if you consider you
know complex templated types then of
course this is very convenient yes it
will be very nice and the other nice
thing about it too is it also means that
if for example you make some changes to
your code so that the types there be
returned from functions maybe change a
little bit yeah then you don't have to
go back and change uni of those type
declarations instead auto automatically
updates things too to be the new type
yeah and I want to emphasize that
everything is still completely
statically type checked yeah so yeah
this is not a dynamic language this is
the compiler essentially figures out
what the type is but you still can't
make type errors in your programs
any more than you would be able to using
your own types yeah and where does this
work you mentioned I think kind of a
local variable declaration does it also
work for parameters like I can probably
can't work there don't worry it doesn't
work for parameters but if you think
about it templates already give you that
capability with parameters if what you
want to say is I have a function that
will take any type of parameter you just
write a template and you say it takes
type T so this is the capability that
the language has always had for
functions so the parameter problem was
never there
you know however what this means now is
that any variable whether it's a global
variable or a local variable pretty much
I have to say pretty much any variable
because member variables actually you
still have to give a type two but
normally if you are declaring a variable
and you give it an initializing
expression then you can use auto on the
other hand if you just say you know you
can't just say Auto I visualize
expression can't figure it out unless
you write Auto with the capital a and
it's actually a class name
haha that you could do okay mm-hmm yeah
I guess yeah I think you've got a C++
programmer deep down inside you
somewhere no well I did some C++
programming a long time ago but never I
never got paid for it so never I never
did it for real okay I do deal quite a
bit with C these days in embedded
systems but without the plus plus
embedded systems in my mind is one of
the places where C++ is likely to be
more important than it has been in the
past I see a lot of use of C++ and
embedded systems mm-hmm especially in
things like video games automotive but
just embedded systems in general yeah
but what I also see quite a bit is that
people kind of go directly from C to
domain-specific languages in code
generation and and consider the C more
or less as something that's generated
anyway so they don't even bother going
to the C++ part not everywhere but
that's what I also seen in quite a bunch
of places interesting yep okay next
topic that I wrote down here is our
value references no idea what this could
mean yeah and and really rather than
talking let me put it this way um there
are two high-level goals that C++ what
hex wanted to be able to offer to people
and the most important one in my opinion
is what's known as move semantics now C
and C++ are both value oriented
languages and the idea is that if I say
for example that X gets Y that after
that X and y have their own separate
chunks of memory and x and y are
completely independent okay so unlike
languages like Java and c-sharp which
have reference semantics where if you
assign one object to another you're
really just assigning a reference
although I can emulate that by using a
reference like you know the ampersand
facility to have two variables pointing
to the same thing but the point there is
that you a under those conditions in C++
you actually have a pointer yes okay I
see when did the language itself
expressly has pointers and so you can
get reference semantics in C++
if you want to but if you just have an
object and you say I want to copy this
object you are going to get a
different copy of that object right and
in fact this rule also applies to
pointers essentially if you have a
pointer and you copy it you get another
copy of that pointer yes so the rule is
completely uniform and this is nice in
in many ways unfortunately at least to
certain kinds of inefficiencies so as an
example if you have let's say a function
which returns a heavyweight object so
maybe it returns a matrix or something
like that
the normal rule in C++ says that you're
going to cut you're going to make a
complete copy of that matrix that gets
returned from the function and sometimes
this is what you want and that's correct
and other times it gives you correct
behavior but it's very inefficient
so the idea behind move semantics in C++
o/x is to allow the compiler to be able
to detect for any arbitrary type
including user-defined types when it is
not necessary to make a copy oh and in
simply move the contents of one object
into the contents of another object so
this is the IdeaPad move semantics it
essentially says I'm going to give the
compiler enough information so that it
will be able to figure out when it
doesn't need to make a copy
even for user-defined types when it
doesn't know what the type means so
that's the idea behind move so many it's
an efficiency improvement and what you
mentioned actually were r-value
references and it turns out that our
value references are a new special kind
of reference in C++ effects that make it
possible to seamlessly implement move
semantics so what we have to do as a
programmer to tell the compiler that in
certain places move semantics is valid
as possible or this is the real sweet
thing you don't have to do anything and
in fact one of the one of the things
that's really nice about move semantics
is if you have a program which is valid
C++ right now and you simply get
yourself a C++ iox compiler which comes
with a C++ Oh X library all you have to
do is
recompile and magically inside your
program places where you were
unnecessarily making copies will start
doing moves instead it will not change
the behavior of your program but it
should improve the efficiency of the
program now on the other hand the idea
behind move semantics says I have an
object and I can move its data from one
object to another I don't need to copy
the data I can move it and it's
especially important for example if you
have a pointer to a data structure on
the heap yeah and what what you is just
copy the pointer rather than copying
everything on the heap yeah vectors of
course different well it actually if you
think about something like a string
strings usually have their data on the
heap yeah so the thing when you when you
when you sew to copy a string in C++
usually means you copy the data on the
heap as well yeah because remember after
the copy you need two completely
independent objects but in some cases
with move semantics the compiler can
figure out that there is in fact no need
to make the copy okay as a result just
move the pointer instead and which is
much more efficient so yeah and what you
what users do need to be able to do is
for an arbitrary type so if I if I've
come up with my own special type with
its own special data structures I do
need to have a way to specify to the
compiler if you decide that you want
move this data from one object to
another how do you do that move now in
C++ we've always had what's called a
copy constructor yeah how do you make a
copy of this thing so in the selects we
now have what are known as move
constructors which allows you to say if
you want to do a move this is how you do
it for this type okay so getting back to
your comment originally about our
actually your question about our value
references our value references are the
underlying language feature that makes
it possible to implement move semantics
but but in my mind for most programmers
the actual feature there
care about is move semantics and not
r-value references right and and for a
typical user defined type like a class
with a bunch of you know members member
fields what is it called as last bus
attributes fields members data members
data members okay do I really have to
implement a move constructor or is the
default behavior good enough for most
cases you know it's interesting that you
should you should ask that because two
weeks ago I would have said that you
have to implement move constructors
yourself regardless because they're not
generated by the compiler but but since
it's now two weeks later and there has
been another standardization meeting one
of the last things that they did before
voting up this final committee draft was
to add the conditions under which move
constructors will automatically be
generated okay and so for for most types
I think it is reasonable to assume that
the compiler will be able to generate a
move constructor for you automatically
cool and if it turns out that that's not
exactly what you would want then of
course you can change the behavior
yourself oh this sounds really
interesting and it's kind of as you said
before
C++ is the language for a kind of
low-level and efficiency oriented
programs and this is another step in
this direction yeah it's also the
language to be honest I mean it's for
efficiency but it's also for control and
so you know sort of the goal is to have
the language do something for you
probably with great efficiency but if
you don't like what it's doing give you
the controls and the knobs to let you
change that behavior right yeah okay and
I mentioned one other thing and I'm
sorry but like I said it's it's a it's a
big improvement it's a big language I'm
because again getting back to our value
references what I said was that there's
two higher level features that are value
references help implement the most
important one I think for most people
will be what's known as move semantics
you know but I want to mention just in
passing the other one is what's known as
perfect forwarding this is a feature
which is really only going to be of
interest to library developers but one
of the challenges which has existed in
C++ is that if you wanted to write a
template that essentially act as a
wrapper and what you really wanted to
say was whatever parameters are passed
to this template
I want to turn around and pass them
exactly the way that I got them to some
other template this is what's known as
the forwarding problem yeah it turned
out there was some very some some
technical issues where you could not
perfectly forward what you got what does
it mean to perfectly forward perfectly
forward means that well one of the
things in people as opposed to X that is
more important than it has been in the
past as R is the different Riel values
and our values and and an L value
essentially is an object whose lifetime
is being controlled by the user and
squint then an R value is an object
whose lifetime is controlled by the
compiler yeah and it turns out that this
distinguishing between the L values and
our values is actually what makes move
semantics work because the compiler
knows what to nail value and the
compiler knows what's an R value and
because it knows that it can figure out
when a move is valid and when it's not
so what this means is when you're
writing a wrapper function what you want
to be able to do is if somebody passed
you in our value it's very important
that you forward as an R value but he
passed you and L value is very important
that you pass it as an L value and when
you get a parameter a parameter has a
name and that means that the programmer
controls the lifetime of that parameter
yeah they can decide to use it and when
not to use it but the problem is if it
was passed in originally as an R value
then because it's now a parameter and it
has a name now it's an L value you have
to have educator nning it back into an R
value and perfect forwarding is the name
that we give for the mechanism that is
used to make that possible I see ok
mm-hmm
and again the underlying implementation
mechanism is based on this new language
feature called r-value references ok I
guess if I really need to understand the
details I really have to take it look at
some code I guess but and I think that's
well but but again it the nice thing is
at a very high level move semantics
simply means that things will be more
efficient without your necessarily doing
anything about it now and perfect
forwarding means that as a library
writer you're going to be able to do
things seamless
that you could not do before yeah yeah
okay the next one very attic if I
pronounced it correctly templates what's
that
yeah very templates means you can write
a template it takes any number of
parameters of any type and manipulate
them in a type safe fashion so up to up
to this point in C++ before C++ so X you
might say I have a template function
that takes five arguments but there was
a way to say I have a template function
that takes an argument
it's like var arcs in in in in Java I
know I don't know about Java but it's
like ver args in C except it's type safe
okay mm-hmm yeah so there you basically
you never lose the type information yeah
so means is now you can write templates
that don't care how many types are
passed in but can manipulate them in a
type safe fashion mm-hmm okay so you
kind of say this function takes
basically an unlimited list of arguments
of type T no you say this function takes
an unlimited list of arguments of any
combination of types they don't all have
to be of type T okay remember I talked
earlier about the async function yeah I
said and I said you can ask that
anything that is executable yep a lot
with any collection of arguments of any
type yep very attic templates are how
you do that I see but then if I write
the implementation of that function how
do i how can how do I know how to treat
each of these things how do I find out
what the you know types are I mean how
can I do anything sensible or can I just
forward them or do something generic
well again it'd be a lot easier effect
if I could show you code but effective
effectively what you do is what you
receive as an implementer is a a collect
you you essentially receive a type safe
list of everything that was passed in
and then using certain programming
techniques you essentially walk down
that list and so you say okay the first
one is of this type let me do this with
it the second one is of this type let me
do this with it so you need some kind of
runtime type information going on
they're all done during compilation this
is still C++ okay remember the compiler
what the types are okay okay let me
rephrase you need some compile time
reflection capability let me put it this
way if I want to it let's suppose I want
to print out some some object of type T
then usually what we've done is we've
overloaded the output operator yeah so
that ever T is it prints in the
appropriate way yep so if it's an int it
prints like an int and if it's a string
it prints like a string so the way we do
that is through overloading yeah so you
never had to say well is this an int or
is this a string you simply let the
compiler go oh this is an int let me
call the appropriate output operator for
an int yeah so very attic templates
essentially do the same thing so you'll
you'll get some some parameter it
happens to be of some type T you don't
know what it is and you're virtually
never going to query what its type is
what you're gonna do instead is you're
going to invoke some operation on it
yeah okay now whatever operation you
invoke is probably overloaded which
means the compiler is gonna
automatically figure out the right one
to call yep I see okay the usual the
usual approach in that in that way yeah
in other words it simply dovetails
really nicely with overloading on fun
types yeah okay the next one I wrote
down is lambda functions now this sounds
a bit functional so it seems like C++ is
going a little bit in the functional
direction I guess you could you can
think of it that way lambda functions
are simply unnamed functions that you
create actually to be quite precise
they're unnamed function objects that
you create on the fly at the point where
you need a statement and I think now
exists in c-sharp and I does Java have
lambda functions as well well no this
whole story about implementing closures
which is kind of the same thing as
lambda functions more or less is it's a
sad story I have lost track about in
which standards they're going to perhaps
yeah I don't know it will come perhaps
at some point I'm not up to date yeah
well anyway so so so lambda functions
are unnamed function objects that you
can create pretty much any tape-based
anyplace a statement is necessary and
they're extremely convenient in two
cases one of the cases were they're very
very convenient
is when you're actually spawning off a
separate threat of control yeah yeah
yeah so for example if you for example
it let's suppose you want to do you you
want to say you want to compute F plus G
and get the answer but you want that to
be done asynchronously yeah
so the really nice thing is you can call
async you create a lambda function the
lambda function has no name you simply
say I want to add F and G together and
async says great I will create a
function object for you here's the
future you know you can now go off and
do your thing yeah so so one really nice
place to use lambda functions is when
you're doing threading is there a
special special syntax then to write
those lambdas down or do I have to do
some let's say weird class thing no
there's a special syntax it turns out
that when you write a lambda function it
looks a lot like a regular function but
what actually happens is the compiler
automatically generates a class for you
says that the appropriate data members
and then does the appropriate okay hmm
it saves you the trouble of writing a
class yeah and the other place where
lambda functions are very convenient is
when you are doing things in the
standard template library yeah yeah oh
if I want to be able things um you know
for example I have a collection I have a
vector of widgets and every widget has I
don't know an age and I've decided that
what I want to do is I want to sort this
vector of widgets in decreasing order
based on their age yeah
and that means any dab some kind of a
special comparison function which will
compare to widgets and return which one
is older and a lambda function is
perfect for that yeah because you don't
write a separate class you don't want to
write a separate function in place you
just want to say sort it based on this
criterion and the lambda function is a
is an economical first way expressing
what you want to do I guess that's the
important thing because I could sum
something people might forget or might
not know is that you could write what
you'd like to maybe want to call
higher-order functions you could always
write them and see bi or C++ I should
say by using functional objects right
but the syntax was kind of ugly and now
so these these lambda functions or they
they just basically they provide a
syntactic abbreviation for building a
function object right exactly
okay hmm yep and and they're very
convenient yeah yeah
I understand that that's yeah Javan it's
this urgently I mean except that by the
time the Java has it I guess everybody
uses Scala which does have nice trouble
these things at least that's my strategy
um so the last language features that I
wrote down before we're going to take a
look at the library is the uniform
initialization syntax and initializer
lists what's that it's two separate
things one of them is uniform
initialization it just turns out that
that from C as well as some stuff in C++
there are a lot of different ways to
initialize things a lot of different
syntaxes so even in C for example you
could say int a equals 5 but but you
could also for example if you had an
array of int then you would say equals
and then you have an open curly brace
and a list of values yeah in C++ we then
added constructors so now you could say
things like you know widget W open paren
a comma B comma C yep so already we have
three syntaxes we have the equal sign to
initialize the end we have the curly
brace list for initializing the array
and we have the parentheses for
initializing the object which calls a
constructor so we have three different
syntaxes and when you start writing
templates this becomes very problematic
because you don't necessarily know what
syntax to use to initialize whatever
your object of type T is yeah so uniform
initialization essentially says we're
going to let you use braces virtually
everywhere okay so so you can initialize
an int using braces you can initialize
an object using braces you can
initialize an array using braces and so
it's called uniform initialization
syntax because the syntax for
initialization is now basically the same
everywhere so I could write int I and
then instead of equals 5 I could opening
curly v closing totally exactly I mean
the equals will continue to work but
sure the new thing the new thing is that
the braces will work ok and furthermore
they will work not just with built-in
types like int they will also work with
user-defined types like you know tree or
customer or whatever you want it to be
yes ok that's a good way to to kind of
write down structure literals if you
will yeah
and and so so it's now so once you
started doing this you so that's kind of
step one of uniform additional ization
well the thing is now let us suppose
that you have a user defined type and
and the user defined type let's suppose
that it's I don't know it's a point and
so you want to have an x value in a Y
value yeah and I guess we're very fancy
this is you know a Z value as well
you've got an X a Y and a Z but let's
suppose you'd also like to have some
kind of a list of weighting factors that
should be applied to this point when
it's used in certain contexts so your
data members are you have let's say an
int X and int Y and an in Z but you also
have let's say a vector of weighting
factors mm-hmm and what that means is
when you're calling the constructor what
you want to pass in is the value for x2
value for Y the value for Z but then you
also want to pass in an arbitrary number
of objects that are supposed to go into
that vector yeah and so now there is a
new thing in the standard library called
an initializer list and an initializer
list is basically a collection of values
that are enclosed in braces which can be
treated as a single thing so it's like a
list a list literal it is it is like it
is like a list literal yeah but but but
then I thing is it now remember we
already have very attic templates so we
can pass in as many arguments as we want
of as many type as we want this allows
us to say I've only got one argument but
it has multiple values it's sort of like
passing in it write a list literal yeah
yeah oh and it works with the same
syntax as uniform initialization okay
nice I've actually played around with
these features because they're in in
some compilers and I have to tell you
that that when you sit down and start
writing little toy programs playing
around these new features you just can't
help but have this big grin breakout on
your face yeah it's just so nicely it's
really very sweet yeah okay before we go
on to the library there is one thing
that I think I heard about the the O X
standard at some point and I think it
was called called concepts is that am I
wrong or is it still in there has it
been deleted what's the status you're
not you're not wrong
concepts were for a long time
going to be the big new marquee feature
for C++ OS exactly yeah and last summer
they were removed from the draft for C++
of X because the standardization
committee as a whole was not able to
agree on some important details of their
specification okay and so so concepts
got removed yes and uh worth discussing
in one or two minutes what would they
would have been concepts effectively
were supposed to make it possible let me
put it this way in Java you have
interfaces and so you might say I'm
gonna write a generic and the generic
has to support interfaces a B and C
mm-hmm correct correct
yeah you can you can write a class
that's genera fide and it can implement
a B and C and the other way you can do
it you can say the type that the generic
parameter of some class has to be a
subtype of the following combination of
other types yeah in other words in Java
you can say I'm gonna take some type T
but he has to implement the following
interface yes right okay
in C++ there's no way to say that
there's no direct way to say that mm-hmm
and furthermore it turns out that that's
not exactly what we want to be able to
say in C++ most of the time what you'd
like to be able to say in people as for
example is that I'm writing a template
it takes an object of type T and T has
to support let's say the plus operation
hi let's say the copy operation and
maybe T has to support the clone
operation yeah in scala that's known as
structural types okay okay so the idea
behind concepts was to give you a syntax
as a template author yeah that would
allow you to specify what these
constraints on the type T are okay okay
that that was the idea behind concepts
and in it and it was the idea the
motivation was number one you'd be able
to give much better error messages if it
turns out that your types didn't support
the right
of operations yep and then it also made
life easier for library implementers in
implementing certain kinds of things
yeah so that was the motivation behind
concepts and they did a tremendous
amount of work on concepts but like I
said last summer so about nine months
ago I think it was last July they the
standardization committee decided that
they were not going to be able to reach
consensus on some very important
technical issues related to concepts and
rather than have that issue keep C++ so
X from from moving forward they simply
decided to remove concepts from this
version of the language but with the
idea of potentially adding it in 25
years to the next C++ standard yeah I
think they're probably the operative
word there is potentially my my my sense
is that the the drive for concepts lost
a lot of steam but we'll see what
happens okay so let's take a look at the
new features in the standard library the
standard library obviously plays an
important especially the container
library again I guess plays an important
part in the c++ c++ world and so what
new stuff do we there do we have there I
guess there must be some stuff for
concurrency right yeah it turns out most
of the concurrency stuff is actually in
the library right so for example you
think you know promise is the class in
the standard library future is actually
more than one class in the standard
library mutex is a classroom standard
library and I should actually mention
that most of these things when I call
them classes almost always they're
actually class templates yeah yeah so
almost everything in the standard
library is a template so a lot of the
concurrency if you know async is a class
template actually async is a function
template so most of that stuff it turns
out there's also some very primitive
support for doing expressions of time in
the standard library and the reason it's
there is because we need to be able to
specify timeouts on certain parts of the
concurrency library so if you want to I
try to acquire a mutex for example but
you don't want to wait more than 10
milliseconds you need to have a way to
specify what ten milliseconds is so
that's that's in the standard library
one of the things that has been proven
to be very useful for C++ programmers is
reference counting
because there's no garbage collection in
the language there's still no garbage
collection in the language yeah but
reference county is what we use in many
cases rather than having everybody
re-implement their own version of
reference counting which aside from
being tedious turns out to be really
very difficult to do in a thread safe
manner if you also want to be efficient
there's now a standard class called
actually a standard class template
called shared pointer which is a
reference counting smart sweater which
automates reference counting and it has
something else a lot so she had with it
called weak pointer which just makes it
easier to make cyclic structures and
observers and stuff like that since you
mentioned a garbage collection you know
this joke about C++ and garbage
collection right no I'm probably not
yeah so that there is this joke which
says why doesn't C++ have garbage
collection and the answer is because
then nothing would be left I'm surprised
you didn't know it curiously enough that
joke doesn't make the C++ circle yes I
have to point out because I take a
certain solace in this in one of the
things that C++ is supposed to be you
know good for is very low-level
efficient programming and so the last
time I checked if you look in the
underlying implementation of the runtime
system of the CLR for dotnet yeah the
the underlying CLR is written in C++
sure and last I heard the hotspot
compiler for Java the core of that is
also written in people as well sure and
and I guess I mean it to me it wouldn't
make any sense to add garbage collection
to C++ exactly for the reasons you just
outlined I mean this is not there's a
different focus it's a different kind of
language otherwise it would become Java
and we already have Java so what's the
point well for what it's worth actually
C++ so X for a while was going to have
some support for garbage collection
there was gonna be actual
optional garbage collection in C++ so X
okay but that got eliminated along the
way yeah not surprised okay I think
regular expressions are now also in C++
standard library right yep yeah now I
mentioned earlier that in 2005 there was
something called TR one F was a should
have 14 libraries
so those have been available in one form
or another since 2005 Oh most of the new
standard library stuff that we're going
to talk about right now is essentially
C++ Oh ex versions of what was in TR one
so regular expressions are one of those
things so yeah we've had in some sense
regular expressions since 2005 we just
have slightly better regular expressions
now and one of the things that makes
them a little bit better for example is
we now have what are known as raw string
literals in C++ so X okay so you specify
a string literal that looks like a
regular expression without having to put
a backslash in front of all the back
slashes yeah yeah make sense oh yes
you've got you've got regular
expressions searching and you've got
regular expression replacing and and
regular expression matching and it's
it's very powerful it's pretty much what
you'd expect from a regular expression
library and this being C++ it's all
templatized so it works on any arbitrary
types that can be considered strings of
symbols ah okay cool so you can you can
build your own kind of let's say
matching facilities for your own
structured data
well the matching algorithms are built
in but for example if you want to if you
want to do it over a you can pass in for
example two iterators so it doesn't
actually care what it he doesn't care
whether it's matching char stars or
launch are stars or or unicode char
stars or your own string custom string
type in other words it's not limited to
a particular collection of types okay
mm-hmm so if you have a type that looks
like it's a sequence of characters you
can use all of the regular expression
machinery on that okay
generalized functors and binders i have
no idea what i should make of that so i
guess you have to explain I mentioned I
mentioned earlier well this will be a
generalized functor is a generalization
of a function pointer okay so that's
this thing that you basically can pass
into async right well I think it's more
general than that I tried yeah I mean
there's a lot of this generalization
stuff essentially let's it let's suppose
let me put it this way in the same way
that a think will take anything that's
callable in some case what you want to
say is I need a variable or often it's a
parameter you often
want to say I need a parameter that can
hold anything that is callable yeah yeah
yeah and and that's what a generalized
functor is so we can point to a function
it can be a function pointer but it can
also point to a function object yeah
okay I see so it's kind of the opposite
I mean if you if you can pass around
functions you should have something that
can hold these things if you pass around
things that act like function tests you
know okay mm-hmm but there might be
functions but they might actually just
be objects that act like functions yeah
yeah okay and a binder gets you you
talked before about for example if you
have a method and you if you pass a
method around in general in C++ when we
are manipulating functions we treat them
as non-member functions syntactically
and what that means is if I have a
method I have to also have an object on
which to invoke that method yep
so I know which object the method should
be invoked on and then you pass
additional parameters and so a
generalized binder among other things
allows you to say okay this is a method
and this is the object I want to invoke
it on let me bind the two of them
together and now I can pass that around
as a function okay mm-hmm but it also
turns out that it allows you to say I
have a regular function or a function
object let's suppose it takes three
arguments and I happen to know at a
particular point in my program I'm doing
some calculation and at a particular
point in my program I know that the
second argument is going to have some
value but I haven't figured out what the
values of the first and the third
arguments are yet yeah I can bind that
second argument value to the function
and thus create a brand new function
object which only takes two arguments
so that's currying it is exactly
currying cool not exactly it's
interesting I mean there's quite a lot
of stuff coming hey I didn't expect that
I mean from good old C++ there's
actually a lot of really interesting
stuff in C++ so X and I'll also mention
that both of these things functors
generalize functors and generalized
binders those again are derivatives of
what was specified in tr1 so they've
been around since 2005 okay well I
didn't notice you weren't C++ there
would have been no reason to
yep hash tables are there's also
something new about them I'm surprised
haven't there always been map kind of
structures in the standard library there
have always been maps and sets but those
were balanced binary search trees so
they were always hash tables are just
what they say they're there they're
actual hash tables that fit in to the
structure of the standard template
library yeah it's something that
everybody wanted and in fact they would
have liked to have them in 1998 it just
turned out that they were it would have
been too much work to nail down the
specification okay so again there
there's something that which were
specified in tr1 okay but there is no
literal syntax for map entries except
that you can of course always you know
you know pass in some kind of template
tuple kind of thing but but there is no
special syntax for hash literals what do
you mean by ahead for example Scala has
it you can basically write something
like so if you have a hash map and you
want to initialize it you can pass in
comma separated lists of values which
basically look like you know key arrow
you know this rocket symbol equals
grater and then the value so the hash
literal is a name value pair literal
with a special syntax
okay you can achieve the same effect
thanks to uniform initialization and
initializer list so a B yeah all right
so you know in other words if what you
want to say is I have a hash table and I
want it to have the following keys and
the following values yeah you can't you
can do that using uniform initialization
you just use braces but you would pass
in the keys and value separately and not
a set of key value pairs and a list of
those well you'd actually put each key
value pair together inside their own set
of braces okay okay okay I get it but
but it looks like it would be this
syntactically it would be the same as if
it were a vector of you know pairs I
mean there is no special syntax for the
fact that it's a hash map but you don't
need that anyway so let me put it this
way that the goal of people's puzzle
works would have would have been to say
you shouldn't have a special syntax for
that I really instead you should use the
same
actually use for any other container
yeah okay which is the same syntax you
use for any other variable yeah makes
sense that's the whole idea behind
uniform initialization syntax yeah yeah
okay that the last thing I had here was
tuples there is some support for tuples
too I guess
yes so I mean I suppose has always had
support for pairs we just you know two
things of arbitrary type so a tuple is
simply an extension of that to an
arbitrary number of components and is
that done the way the way it's done in
Scala I think is that there is 23
classes you know tuple to tuple 3 tuple
4 to 5 up till tuple 22 I think is it
done the same way or is there some more
template magic bar or X bariatric stuff
going on
Thanks thanks to very attic templates
yeah you only have to write one you
write one template and you say it takes
an arbitrary number of objects an
arbitrary number of types and it just
works
nice huh so there's a and as a result
there's no there's no you don't have to
impose a limit of like okay you can't
have more than 23 different components
of a double well as soon as somebody has
a tuple 23 I guess there is some
refactoring potential anyway well I just
want to mention in passing because it is
important in practice it is not uncommon
for people to have code that is
generated by machine rather than by and
when you have machines writing code that
it's not uncommon for example that
functions which take a hundred
parameters no human would do that
but a machine might and so it's not in
my experience it is not uncommon to have
machine generated code look like really
awful human written code well I think
it's the languages support that I spent
almost all my professional time work
building domain-specific languages and
code generators and if a customer you
know with whom I'd work wrote a
generator that would generate that kind
of code I would say you know why don't
you write a generator that generates
readable code but that's another story
yeah which would be fair enough yeah ok
so anything else anything we missed
any additional thing that just came to
your mind that you kind of want to
mention about because otherwise I think
we're kind of through um I'm just gonna
make all I'm gonna say is that we have
not talked by any means about everything
that is in C++ Oh X and we've certainly
hit the high points but but as I said
when I when I first stood out and looked
at it I sort of thought there's gonna be
a few new features but there's a whole
ton of stuff you know I mean there's a
lot more control over exactly when the
compiler generates certain kinds of
functions and what they do and so you
know we've hit at least we've talked
about most of the things but we haven't
talked about everything yeah Mikey means
so during the preparation the little
that I did for this episode I I I
googled a little bit and I found among
other things a really nice Wikipedia
page about the new features and I
thought it's it was it probably wasn't
complete but it was was understandable
and readable so I guess I'll put that
into the show notes do you have any
other suggestions where people can find
further information about this stuff
also I'll send you a couple links one of
the things that I'd want to mention is a
lot of these features exist in at least
one compiler right now and so like when
I talk about you know it's really fun to
play with these things I'm actually
talking about writing programs that will
compile and and that will do something
so the actual experience that we have
with these things so I'll send you a
link to a page that I've put together
which summarizes for visual C++ and also
for GCC which features they support but
it also has some links to another
Wikipedia page that shows a couple of
other summaries of which compilers
support these features because I do
think it's important for people to
understand this is not a theoretical
language thing we have to wait until
2011 to use it you can start using a lot
of it right now and it's something I
definitely encourage people to play
around with because it's a very sweet
language to program in very nice and in
the worst case if they don't get it you
will probably you know they can probably
convince you to to sell you know some
consulting or training I mean if it
really you know if it's really necessary
III well I mean there's a lot of stuff
there you know the it's like anything
else you know the easy features are
clear and straightforward when it gets
down to for example writing the code to
walk the list of very otic templates and
do something with each parameter it's
not hard to do once you know how to do
it by learning how to do it takes a
little bit of time yeah okay then Scott
I guess I thank you very much for being
on the show
I thought this was a very good very
interesting episode and well thank you
well thank you very much for having me I
appreciate it good great bye all right
bye-bye
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineer
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at se - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the AC
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at SC - radio net or if they're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
creative commons two-point-five license
please see the website for details
thanks to Charlie Crowell and the pot
site Music Network for the music used in
this show the song is called Vegas on
top